<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the King at White-Hall, January the 9th 1675[/]6 By Thomas Cartwright, D.D. chaplain in ordinary to His Majesty. Published by His Majesties special command.</title>
            <author>Cartwright, Thomas, 1634-1689.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80865</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C702B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4730</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899406</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899406</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153082</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80865)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153082)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 841:17; 2346:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the King at White-Hall, January the 9th 1675[/]6 By Thomas Cartwright, D.D. chaplain in ordinary to His Majesty. Published by His Majesties special command.</title>
                  <author>Cartwright, Thomas, 1634-1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>35, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In the Savoy: printed by T. Newcomb, and are to be sold by Jonathan Edwyn, at the Three Roses in Ludgate-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached St. Jude 22, 23. St. Jude 22, 23. at White-Hall.</note>
                  <note>Identified on UMI microfilm as Wing C702, but is actually C702B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Jude I, 22-23 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153082:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED before the KING AT WHITE-HALL, <hi>January</hi> the 9th 1675/6.</p>
            <p>BY THOMAS CARTWRIGHT, D. D. Chaplain in Ordinary to His <hi>MAJESTY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by His Majeſties ſpecial Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>SAVOY:</hi> Printed by <hi>T. Newcomb,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Jonathan Edwyn,</hi> at the Three Roſes in <hi>Ludgate-ſtreet.</hi> 1676.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:153082:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:153082:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>St. JUDE, Verſ. 22, 23.</bibl>
                  <p>And of ſome have compaſſion, making a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence: And others ſave with fear, pulling them out of the fire; hating even the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſpotted by the fleſh.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Man whoſe Soul is once Effectually wrought upon by the <hi>Spirit of Grace,</hi> beſtows his firſt and chief care in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit of Salvation: for he then ſees how deep, how ſpread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and how mortal an infection Sin is, and is throughly convinced of the manifold danger of every particular Iniquity; in as much, as it puts a Man into a ſtate of Enmity againſt God, and his Laws, and ſo <note place="margin">Rom. 7. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>worketh Death, and that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal:</hi> and therefore he cannot reſt, until he be reſolv'd of that <hi>Important Quaere,</hi> which was ſtarted by the <hi>Pagan Jaylor</hi> to <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas, Sirs, What muſt I do to be ſaved?</hi> And, being converted himſelf, he becomes very ſollicitous (as St. <hi>Peter</hi> was commanded to be) for the <note place="margin">Luk. 22. 32.</note> 
                  <hi>ſtrengthening of his Brethren;</hi> and doth what in him lies, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> rouze them out of their Senſuality,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153082:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> that they may not ſleep ſecurely in their Sins, till Eternal Flames become their <hi>firſt Awakners.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is indeed a Catholick and comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Duty, and directed accordingly, as this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle is, <note place="margin">Verſ. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Omnibus Chriſti Fidelibus, To all that are Sanctified by God the Father.</hi> But, becauſe that which is <hi>every Mans</hi> Work, is <hi>no Mans</hi> Work; as God ſent his <hi>Angel</hi> to bring <hi>Lot</hi> out of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and conduct him to <hi>Zoar;</hi> ſo, that you might never want <hi>Men</hi> to guide you to the City of Refuge, when the Avenger purſues you, God hath committed to us the care of your Souls, and given us Commiſſion to invite you to be Reconciled to him, and to accept of that Everlaſting Entertainment which he hath provided for you; and, rather then fail, to <hi>Compel</hi> you to come in to his <hi>Manſions of Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And, becauſe we ſhall meet with <hi>Men</hi> in the World of as <hi>different tempers,</hi> as <hi>complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> he hath alſo given us ſufficient Inſtructions, how to demean our ſelves towards them; bids us, not ſerve all our <hi>Patients</hi> out of the ſame <hi>Box;</hi> but, like skilful <hi>Phyſitians,</hi> apply different <hi>Medicines</hi> according to the difference of their <hi>Maladies;</hi> to manage the Word of God, and our Miniſtery of Reconciliation, with ſuch
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153082:3"/> Spiritual Skill, and Wiſdom, as to give every one his proper portion. Some <hi>Mens</hi> Hearts are like ſoft Wax, the heat of the <hi>Hand</hi> will make them yield, without that of the <hi>Fire;</hi> a gentle <hi>Admonition</hi> will prevail more with them, than a dreadful <hi>Commination;</hi> they have <hi>Ingenuity</hi> enough to be <hi>ſham'd</hi> out of their Sins upon the leaſt diſcovery: Others are ſo hardned in their Villanies, that they muſt be <hi>ſcar'd,</hi> or <hi>whipt</hi> out of them, as the <hi>Buyers</hi> and <hi>Sellers</hi> were out of the <hi>Temple,</hi> before they will leave them; they, who ſin out of <hi>infirmity,</hi> may be won with <hi>gentle</hi> means, but <hi>Obstinate Offenders</hi> are to be humbled with <hi>terrours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Every <hi>Man</hi> hath his Ignorances and Inadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencies, his Miſtakes and Errours, Infirmities and Indiſcretions; in any of which, if he be at any time <hi>overtaken,</hi> or ſin out of <hi>blind Zeal,</hi> you muſt neither <hi>inſult</hi> over his fall, nor <hi>deſpair of his riſing,</hi> but <hi>restore him with meekneſs;</hi> for he ſins, not by <hi>Deſign,</hi> but <hi>Folly;</hi> he falls, not by <hi>Malice,</hi> but by <hi>Surprize;</hi> not by the <hi>Strength of his Will,</hi> but by the <hi>Frailty of his Nature:</hi> If he be wavering and unſteady in the Faith, you muſt <hi>recover him with mildneſs;</hi> and, if his fault be ſmall, cover it with the <hi>Vail of pity</hi> and <hi>compaſſion,</hi> and uſe gentle means to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153082:4"/> cure him. But yet <hi>make a difference,</hi> if you meet with Men, whoſe Diſtempers are <hi>Inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate,</hi> and Incorporated into their Natures by <hi>Evil Cuſtoms,</hi> your Remedies muſt be <hi>ſharp and quick;</hi> if their ſin be <hi>bold,</hi> your reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion muſt not be <hi>baſhful:</hi> The Chirurgion muſt bring the Saw and the Cauſtick to ſuch Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>green'd Members, proclaim the Terrours of the Lord to them, who <hi>will not ſtand in awe,</hi> but <note place="margin">Heb. 10. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>ſin wilfully, after they have received the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Truth;</hi> Sheathe the Two edged Sword of <hi>Gods Word</hi> in their Bowels; give them a Proſpect of the Approaching Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which will ſuddenly overtake them, if they do not <hi>flee for their Lives:</hi> Suffer them not to look upon the Wrath to come, at the wrong end of the Proſpective-Glaſs; but, <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Terrours of the Lord, uſe an holy Violence,</hi> and ſnatch them rudely out of that Fire, which will <hi>Singe</hi> them, if they ſtay but a minute in it, and will <hi>Devour</hi> them, if their continuance be any longer, and bring them (if it be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible) to the hatred of all <hi>the beginnings,</hi> and <hi>leaſt degrees</hi> of Impurity and Uncleanneſs; make them ſo afraid of the Infection of Fleſhly Luſts, as to avoid the <hi>very Garments that are ſpotted with</hi> it: If private Admonitions do not Reclaim
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153082:4"/> them, proceed to publick; and rather than not pull them out of the flames of Hell, <hi>Cut them off from the Communion of the Faithful,</hi> and <hi>deliver them up to Satan,</hi> to which the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> refers, Reprove them ſharply, when they are Convinc'd, or Separated by <hi>Church-Cenſures;</hi> when they are debarr'd from ſitting at their Fathers Table with the reſt of their Brethren, which (although they may be an inſtance of Severe Diſcipline) are yet with deſigns of great Mercy, (the moſt dreadful of them being <hi>Medicinal,</hi> not <hi>Mortal</hi>) that, by puniſhment of the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> the <hi>Soul</hi> may be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the Day of the Lord: <hi>And of ſome have compaſſion, making a difference: And others ſave with fear, pulling them out of the Fire; hating even the Garment ſpotted by the Fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe words may poſſibly have an eye to <hi>Church Diſcipline,</hi> and be intended as a <hi>Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> to the Governours of the Church, for the Exerciſing, not only of <hi>the milder part</hi> of the Apoſtolical Office, but alſo of thoſe <hi>higher de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Cenſures,</hi> (call'd, <hi>The coming with a Rod</hi>) which, in caſe of Obſtinacy, is not only <hi>Seaſonable,</hi> but <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>navoidable:</hi> But I ſhall ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſider them at preſent, either as they
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153082:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> concern <hi>our ſelves</hi> in the Actions of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, or <hi>our Brethren</hi> in thoſe of Fraternal Correction, and ſo may Inſtruct <hi>all Men,</hi> but eſpecially us of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> how to behave our ſelves towards all, even the <hi>worſt of recoverable</hi> Sinners.</p>
               <p>Now, as our Patients and their Diſtempers are different, ſo muſt alſo our Preſcriptions and Directions be; a <hi>Green Wound</hi> and an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcer</hi> are not to be Cured with the ſame Application: And, that I may make no other difference but what our <hi>Apoſtle</hi> himſelf hath done, nor be tempted to forſake the Scope and Method of my <hi>Text,</hi> I ſhall diſtinctly ſort what I have to ſay, into a Practical Reſolution of theſe Four Inquiries.
<list>
                     <item>I. Of whom it is that we are to have Compaſſion, and with what difference? How that Compaſſion is to be expreſs'd and exercis'd?</item>
                     <item>II. How far we may be inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal to the Salvation of others? and with what fear and caution we muſt attempt it?</item>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:153082:5"/>
                     <item>III. What is meant by <hi>Pulling them out of the Fire?</hi> What that Phraſe <hi>implies,</hi> and what it <hi>requires</hi> of us?</item>
                     <item>IV. What is meant by <hi>Hating the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſpotted by the Fleſh?</hi> and, how it is our <hi>Intereſt,</hi> as well as our <hi>Duty,</hi> to do ſo.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <p>I. <hi>Of ſome have compaſſion.</hi> This noble and generous Affection of <hi>compaſſion,</hi> is ſo <hi>Eſſential</hi> to a Man, ſo rivetted to his very <hi>Being,</hi> and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted in his <hi>Nature,</hi> that, unleſs he degenerate from his <hi>Humanity,</hi> he cannot obſerve, but he muſt alſo condole the Calamities of his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, out of that relation which he bears to <hi>the Species of Mankind;</hi> and, by how much the <hi>more noble</hi> any Man is, by ſo much is he the <hi>more compaſſionate;</hi> and, as all Natural Perfections and Excellencies are <hi>improv'd by Religion,</hi> ſo <hi>this</hi> eſpecially, and that <hi>Spiritual Conſanguinity</hi> which ariſes from our <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> muſt needs make us ſuffer by way of conſent and ſympathy with our fellow Chriſtians, eſpecially when they groan under the burden of their Sins, which of all Loads is the greateſt.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:153082:6"/>
               <p>So great a Lover of Mankind was our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he could not, but with wet Eyes, behold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> preſent Sins and future Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of his moſt inveterate Enemies. Nor is he a Living Member of that <hi>Body,</hi> of which <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the <hi>Head,</hi> who doth not <hi>grieve for the Afflictions of</hi> Joſeph, <hi>and mourn over the Sins</hi> of his Brethren. Would it not make your Hearts ake, to ſee your Neighbours Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes on Fire about their Ears, and them <hi>faſt aſleep</hi> in their Beds? And, if you have the leaſt ſpark of <hi>Chriſtianity or Compaſſion</hi> in your Breaſts, how can your Souls chuſe but be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved within you, to ſee them falling inſenſibly into thoſe Everlaſting Flames, out of which there will be no redemption? This is not only a moſt <hi>neceſſary Charity</hi> to our Brethrens Souls, but ſuch a <hi>Chriſtian Duty,</hi> as makes it an <hi>Act of Righteouſneſs</hi> too, for we <hi>are Members one of another;</hi> nor hath <hi>Chriſt</hi> given us any <hi>Bill of Divorce,</hi> whereby we are ſeparated from the care of our Neighbours, whom we are to love as our ſelves. A Man truly ingrafted into <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is therefore a Common Bleſſing, of a Communicative Spirit, his large Heart is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſet upon <hi>doing Publick Good,</hi> a Duty which hath been ſo long <hi>out of faſhion,</hi> that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153082:6"/> Men begin to queſtion, Whether it be a Duty or not? their <hi>Lives</hi> do at leaſt ſpeak the ſame Language which <hi>Cain</hi> did with his Lips, <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Am I my Brothers Keeper?</hi> and, Where ſhall we find a Man of St. <hi>Bernard</hi>'s temper? who thought himſelf concern'd, whereſoever God or his Brethren were ſo? <note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Hamericum Cancellar.</note> 
                  <hi>Etſi non tanti ſum ut Romae habeam propria negotia, nulla tamen quae Dei eſſe conſtiterit, a me duco aliena.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If ever <hi>Bowels of Compaſſion</hi> were <hi>fit to put on,</hi> it is in this <hi>Wicked Age</hi> of ours; and 'tis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed for want of being mindful of <hi>our own,</hi> that we become ſo regardleſs of <hi>other Mens</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns: for Compaſſion is firſt learn'd <hi>at home,</hi> and then walks <hi>abroad.</hi> I muſt firſt take my Brother <hi>into my ſelf,</hi> before I can pity him as I ought; and having felt the anguiſh of <hi>a Broken Spirit</hi> in my ſelf, I cannot chuſe but <hi>pity it</hi> in another: When <note place="margin">Pſal. 102. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>my Bones are burnt as an Hearth,</hi> and I have felt the <hi>Scorching Flames of Sin</hi> in my own Boſom, I ſhall eaſily think my ſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, to <hi>ſnatch my Brother out of that Fire;</hi> having been deeply affected with the guilt of mine own Iniquities, I ſhall be quickly invited to let my Compaſſionate Soul go through this preſent evil World, as through an <hi>Hoſpital</hi> or <hi>Bedlam,</hi> and into whatſoever corner I caſt mine
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153082:7"/> Eyes, I ſhall behold great Objects of Pity, and be conſtrained to weep for them, who have not ſo much ſenſe of their miſery as to weep for themſelves.</p>
               <p>When we behold Men rock'd aſleep in the Cradle of Security, and never dreaming of Heaven or Hell, of Death or Judgment, but <hi>Courting</hi> their Miſeries, and <hi>Embracing</hi> their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching Ruine, as if they had combin'd to <hi>drive on the Intereſt,</hi> and get <hi>Poſſeſsion</hi> of the Kingdom of Satan; when we ſee ſome groap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>in the dark,</hi> others taking great care and pains to <hi>blow out the light</hi> which would diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Happineſs to them; Men Sick of <hi>Mortal Diſeaſes,</hi> and yet like the <hi>Drunken Lapithae,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing their <hi>Phyſitians;</hi> ſo <hi>deſperately</hi> tainted with Impurity, that, like <hi>Sodom and Gomorrah,</hi> nothing but <hi>Fire from Heaven</hi> can be applyed to them; when we ſee how near their <hi>ſhort-liv'd Happineſs</hi> is expiring, and how ſuddenly their <hi>Imaginary Pleaſures</hi> will be exchang'd into <hi>Real and Eternal Torments,</hi> what can we <hi>do leſs,</hi> and indeed, what can we <hi>do more</hi> than bewail them? <note place="margin">St. Bern.</note> 
                  <hi>Nunquid in te ſunt viſcera pietatis, qui plangis corpus a quo receſsit anima, &amp; non plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis animam a qua receſsit Deus?</hi> Will <hi>pity</hi> move you to bewail that <hi>Body</hi> from whence
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153082:7"/> the <hi>Soul</hi> is departed? and <hi>piety</hi> not conſtrain you to lament that <hi>Soul,</hi> from whence <hi>God</hi> is departed? He, who hath any <hi>bowels of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsion</hi> in him, muſt needs be affected with ſuch a diſmal ſpectacle, and expreſs his <hi>deep ſenſe</hi> of it, and ſorrow for it; not only in the <hi>melting</hi> of his fluent Eyes, and the <hi>yearnings of his Bowels;</hi> but alſo in ſuch an <hi>active compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> and in ſuch ſerious attempts, as may relieve and reſtore them.</p>
               <p>Having therefore the <hi>Nature of the Crime,</hi> the <hi>Fitneſs of the Seaſon,</hi> and, the <hi>Quality of the Perſon offending,</hi> always before our Eyes, let us come to him, <hi>in the cool of the day,</hi> and invite him to take cognizance and compaſſion of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, leſt he Ride Poſt into Hell for want of one to ſtop him; and, that he may not have cauſe to ſay, you come to <hi>caſt out Satan by Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, one Devil by another;</hi> be ſure to do it with ſuch a <hi>compoſed Spirit,</hi> as befits ſo Compaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and Divine a Work: The ſharp ſeverity of a diſeaſed Mind, will rather <hi>ſpur him on,</hi> in the career of his Crimes, than <hi>reſtrain</hi> him; ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make him <hi>flee out</hi> with more ſpeed and violence, than <hi>moderate</hi> or amend him; and therefore let us not through <hi>Pride,</hi> or <hi>Animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity,</hi> out of <hi>an itch of Government,</hi> or the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153082:8"/> of an angry Mind,</hi> run beyond the gentleneſs of Chriſtian Monitors, (unto which <hi>if they hearken, we have won our Brethren:</hi>) but, if they will <hi>obſtinately periſh,</hi> after all our Care and Compaſſion, we ſhall <hi>ſave our ſelves,</hi> becauſe we would have <hi>ſav'd them:</hi> We may <hi>loſe our Labour,</hi> but we ſhall not <hi>loſe our Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> if after we have <hi>forewarn'd</hi> them of the danger, they will yet make <hi>ſo mad a choice</hi> as <hi>to take Hell by violence;</hi> their Obſtinacy is <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonable,</hi> and we muſt ſit down and bemoan our <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſucceſsful Endeavours.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gloſs.</note> 
                  <hi>Miſeremini con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolendo quod non poteſtis eos ſalvare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alas! <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>The Natural Man perceiveth not the things of the Spirit of God, for they are fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to him; neither can he know them, becauſe they are Spiritually diſcerned:</hi> But <hi>he that is Spiritual judgeth all things:</hi> He ſees <hi>by Faith</hi> the <hi>Heaven,</hi> which you neglect, and thoſe <hi>Bleſſed Souls</hi> now in Glory, whoſe <hi>Everlaſting Companions</hi> you might be, if you pleas'd; and he ſees alſo <hi>your Brethrens deſpairing Souls now in Hell,</hi> among thoſe Devils that deceived them, who came thither the <hi>ſame way</hi> you are going in; and with his <hi>Bodily Eyes,</hi> doth he alſo ſee at the ſame time a multitude of <hi>Senceleſs and Senſual Sinners</hi> living round about
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153082:8"/> him, who lay none of theſe things to heart, but damn and defile not only <hi>their own,</hi> but <hi>their Brethrens Souls</hi> by their Errours, Sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and Ungodly Examples, as if they were the <hi>Devils Factors,</hi> under <hi>Commiſſion from him</hi> to make <hi>Proſelytes for Hell,</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly he cannot but compaſſionate their ſad Condition, and wonder at their Stupidity. Oh! What a <hi>Beſotting Thing</hi> is <hi>Sin,</hi> which can thus <hi>petrifie</hi> the Reaſonable Soul, and make <hi>Men</hi> more inſenſible than Beaſts which periſh? What a <hi>Bedlam</hi> is this wicked World, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Thouſands are ſo <hi>diſtracted,</hi> as to make it <hi>their Buſineſs</hi> to <hi>undo themſelves and others</hi> to all Eternity? Can we not bring you to ſome <hi>ſober</hi> thoughts of your condition? Can we not perſwade you to take <hi>Chriſt's part,</hi> and <hi>your own,</hi> againſt the Devil, the World, and the Fleſh, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich you have renounc'd in your Baptiſm? If <hi>Importunity</hi> could prevail with an <hi>unrighteous Judge,</hi> to do good <hi>to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> how much more ſhould it prevail with <hi>you,</hi> to do good to <hi>your ſelves?</hi> Have Mercy therefore upon your own Souls, and do not render it impoſſible for us to be any farther ſerviceable to them. God himſelf will not ſave you <hi>againſt your Wills,</hi> much leſs can <hi>we</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:153082:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> do it; which will the better appear, when I ſhall have given you a ſatisfactory anſwer to the ſecond Inquiry, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <p>2. How far we may be inſtrumental to the Salvation of other Men? and with what fear and caution we muſt attempt it? As there is no good ſo great, as that which reſpects the Souls of Men; ſo certainly, to be a <hi>Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worker</hi> with Chriſt, as an Agent in it, or Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it, muſt needs out-vie all other Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges: And, if the Heathens miſtook <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> for <hi>Gods in the likeneſs of Men,</hi> for <hi>restoring the Criple of</hi> Lyſtra <hi>to his Limbs</hi> again; with much better reaſon may we magnifie them, who have ſo much <hi>Communion with God upon Earth,</hi> as to become <hi>Coadjutors with him</hi> in the Salvation of a Soul from Sin. <note place="margin">Dionyſ. Carthuſ.</note> 
                  <hi>Divina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum omnium perfectionum diviniſſima est perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio, cooperatorum eſſe, in reduc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ne animarum ad ſuum creatorem.</hi> Now God hath given <hi>all Men</hi> ſome <hi>ſpecial Powers and Ministries,</hi> whereby they may Charitably <hi>advance</hi> the great Intereſt of Souls: St. <hi>Paul</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 16.</note> aſſerts the poſſibility of the Chriſtian <hi>Wives ſaving her <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelieving Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band;</hi> and he tells <hi>Timothy,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4. 16.</note> that in <hi>taking heed to himſelf and his Doctrine, he ſhould both ſave himſelf, and them that heard him;</hi> and he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153082:9"/>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>became all things to all men, that he might by all means ſave ſome;</hi> And, <hi>The Salvation of a Soul from death,</hi> is attributed to <hi>the Inſtruments</hi> of their Converſion, by St. <hi>James,</hi> to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them to <hi>diligence</hi> in their Office: Save them; that is, <note place="margin">Aquin.</note> 
                  <hi>Quantum in vobis eſt, ut ſalven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur orate.</hi> Pray for their Converſion, and, if by any means you can, <note place="margin">Rom. 11. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>provoke them to emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> bring them to Faith and Repentance, that you may ſave them.</p>
               <p>Alas! it is <hi>God alone</hi> who can <hi>pierce the ſcales</hi> of this <hi>Leviathan,</hi> and make the <hi>hearts</hi> of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durate Sinners feel, which are <hi>harder than the nether Milstone.</hi> We are but as <hi>Striplings</hi> againſt that <hi>Goliah:</hi> Our <hi>Commiſſion</hi> is indeed from the Almighty, and in his Name we are come forth to wreſtle, <hi>not with Fleſh and Blood, but with Principalities and Powers, and the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the darkneſs of this World;</hi> and, it is <hi>our God</hi> who muſt chooſe out <hi>the Stones that we ſling,</hi> and carry them to the mark, and make them <hi>ſink,</hi> not into the <hi>forehead,</hi> but into <hi>the hearts of theſe uncircumciſed Philiſtins,</hi> and <hi>ſmite them to the ground,</hi> that, with <hi>Saul,</hi> they may <hi>get ſtrength</hi> by their very falls. We can but <hi>Woo and Warn you,</hi> we cannot <hi>Compel</hi> you to be happy, I wiſh we could. <note place="margin">Cornel. a Lapide.</note> 
                  <hi>A Medico &amp; Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:153082:10"/> 
                  <hi>requiritur cura, non curatio; utpote cum morbus non raro ſit incurabilis.</hi> If you will follow our Preſcriptions, <hi>your Diſeaſes</hi> are <hi>not incurable;</hi> have <hi>pity</hi> therefore on your periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Souls, and <hi>cloſe</hi> with the preſent Overtures of Mercy. God hath ſent <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> to <hi>You,</hi> as he did his <hi>Holy Angel</hi> to <hi>Lot,</hi> to lay the Merciful Hands of an <hi>Holy Violence</hi> upon you, that you may <hi>not ſtay any longer</hi> in your Sins, but <hi>eſcape for your Lives,</hi> leſt you be conſumed: If <hi>you are afraid</hi> of theſe enſuing Judgments, <hi>we</hi> are afraid <hi>with you;</hi> if not, we are <hi>afraid for you,</hi> and we are the <hi>more afraid</hi> for you, <hi>the leſs</hi> you are for your ſelves; <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 120.</note> 
                  <hi>Our Fleſh trembles for fear of you, and we are afraid of God's Judgments.</hi> 'Tis with an <hi>aking Heart, and trembling Hand,</hi> that the <hi>Chirurgion</hi> cuts off the Gangreen'd Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of his Boſom-Friend; and, it is alſo with <hi>great Compaſſion,</hi> and no leſs <hi>Fear,</hi> that we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to recover you out of <hi>that Fire,</hi> which will <hi>ſinge</hi> you, if you ſtay but one moment longer in it, and <hi>devour you</hi> as infallibly, if you do not, <hi>whilſt it is called To Day, eſcape it;</hi> the great <hi>importance and difficulty</hi> of which undertaking of yours, will appear, if you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider in the third place,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:153082:10"/>
               <div type="introduction">
                  <p>III. What is meant, by <hi>Pulling them out of the Fire,</hi> and how we muſt do it? What the phraſe <hi>implies,</hi> and what it <hi>requires of us?</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Save them by <hi>ſnatching them out of the Fire,</hi> is a Proverbial <hi>ſpeech</hi> for thoſe who get hardly out of danger; <note place="margin">Amos 4. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>I have overthrown ſome of you, as God overthrew So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Gomorrah, and ye were as a Fire brand pluck'd out of the Burning:</hi> And, <note place="margin">Zac. 3. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>Is not this a Brand pluckt out of the Fire?</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>He himſelf ſhall be ſaved, yet ſo as by Fire;</hi> that is, He ſhall awake and <hi>leap out</hi> of Danger, as a Man at Midnight doth naked out of his Bed, at the Door or Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, when his Houſe is on Fire: which words do accordingly import theſe four things:
<list>
                        <item>1. The great <hi>Danger</hi> of Impenitent Sinners.</item>
                        <item>2. The <hi>Poſſibility</hi> of their <hi>Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. The <hi>Difficulty</hi> of eſcaping their Imminent and Everlaſting Deſtruction.</item>
                        <item>4. By <hi>what Means</hi> it is, that we may Charitably <hi>aſſiſt them</hi> in their eſcape? and which will be the <hi>only poſſible way</hi> of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it?</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="subsection">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:153082:11"/>
                  <p>1. The condition of every <hi>impenitent Sinner</hi> is very <hi>deſperate,</hi> and his danger greater than we can poſſibly imagine; for, <note place="margin">Matth. 5. 22.</note> he is <hi>not only in danger of the Judgment, or of the Council,</hi> but alſo of <hi>Hell-Fire,</hi> which is always inkindled even in this life; here it <hi>burns inwardly,</hi> but there it <hi>blazes out.</hi> When we conſider with what variety of <hi>Temptations</hi> the Devil ſtrives to beguile you, how many <hi>Deſigns</hi> and <hi>Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems</hi> he hath laid in the World to undermine and enſnare you; and, that if all <hi>the Powers of Darkneſs</hi> can hinder it, we ſhall never diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intangle you out of his ſnares: and, when we ſee you <hi>live ſo ſecurely,</hi> as if your pretious <hi>Souls were</hi> already <hi>bound up in the Bundle of Life,</hi> even when they are ready to drop irreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verably into Hell; and when you <hi>prepare</hi> no more <hi>to meet God,</hi> whilſt in wrath he ſeems to approach you, than if you <hi>cared not</hi> whether he came or no; Your <hi>looſe and diſſolute,</hi> your <hi>finful and ſecure</hi> courſes, do evidently ſhew, that <hi>there is no fear of God before your eyes. Sampſon,</hi> for all his <hi>ſtrength</hi> and <hi>ſtoutneſs,</hi> durſt not lie ſtill, when he heard that the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> were come upon him: Where there is an apprehenſion of ſome great <hi>Evil impendent,</hi> there cannot but be a great meaſure of <hi>Fear,</hi>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:153082:11"/> and where ſo great fear, there no leſs vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>deſire to eſcape;</hi> and where there is ſuch a vehement deſire, there will be a moſt ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and <hi>careful endeavour of preventing</hi> (if by any means it may be) of that evil: But when none of theſe appear, but men <hi>go on confidently</hi> in their <hi>evil ways,</hi> as if there were <hi>no danger</hi> of their Damnation; it concerns <hi>us</hi> to try, if we can <hi>ſhake</hi> this their <hi>carnal confidence,</hi> which is founded upon <hi>Abſurdity, Impoſſibility and Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy,</hi> and is not <hi>in Christ,</hi> but <hi>against him:</hi> as if they took <hi>him</hi> for a <hi>Falſe Prophet,</hi> and his <hi>Denunciations</hi> of future Judgments for meer <hi>Deluſions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So <hi>ſervilely diſingenuous</hi> is our <hi>corrupt nature,</hi> that the propoſal of <hi>Rewards,</hi> though never ſo great, doth, in no proportion, lead us ſo forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to our Intereſt and Duty, as do the <hi>Threats and Menaces</hi> of Puniſhment; and therefore God is far more obliging to us in the <hi>ſevereſt of his Temporal Judgments,</hi> than he would be in <hi>his Mercies;</hi> we being a People whom <hi>Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance only</hi> can reclaim; whom nothing but <hi>Terrours</hi> can allure to Goodneſs; and, who need ſome <hi>preſent Flaſhes</hi> of Hell-fire to <hi>ſcare</hi> us from embracing thoſe Future and Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Flames. Leſt therefore the <hi>Meſſenger
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:153082:12"/> of death</hi> ſhould hurry you away in the heat and violence of your Sins, and there <hi>be none to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you from the Worm that dieth not, and the Fire which is not quenched;</hi> we, who <hi>watch for your Souls,</hi> are to do <hi>what we can</hi> to ſtartle you into the amendment of your Lives. And Oh that I could but uncover the face of the <hi>deep and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring Gulph of Tophet</hi> in all its Terrours, and <hi>open the Grate</hi> of that Infernal Furnace! for if you had but any the leaſt degree of <hi>Spiritual Life and Senſe in you,</hi> (and <hi>the Light which is in you were not Darkneſs</hi>) you could not <hi>look in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Hell</hi> by a preſent Contemplation, but you would make it the <hi>Grand Deſign</hi> of your Lives to eſcape the <hi>falling into it,</hi> by a future Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Hide not your ſelves from your own Souls, and <hi>they</hi> will tell you, that there is but yet <hi>a ſtep</hi> between you and Hell: But if you are <hi>Obſtinati ad moriendum,</hi> ſturdily reſolved <hi>not to underſtand</hi> your Miſery and Danger, till it be <hi>paſt prevention,</hi> there is an end of all our hopes concerning you. If you have the Reaſon and Underſtanding of Men, you will not dare to leap into the Bottomleſs-Pit <hi>with your Eyes open,</hi> nor to <hi>dally</hi> with the Vengeance of the <hi>Almighty.</hi> Will you ſit ſtill till the <hi>Tide</hi> come in, and then harden your ſelves with a vain
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:153082:12"/> conceit, that you ſhall <hi>eſcape drowning?</hi> If <hi>we</hi> cannot undeceive you, the <hi>King of Terrours</hi> ſhortly will; for when Death <hi>ſtrikes its Dart through your Liver,</hi> it will let out <hi>your Souls and Hopes together</hi> into the Amazing Gulph of Endleſs Deſperation. We dare not therefore <hi>daub your Conſciences with ſuch untempered Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar,</hi> as to flatter you into a <hi>Fatal Opinion</hi> of the <hi>Safety of your Condition;</hi> but think, we oblige you moſt, when we ſhew you, <hi>how dear your Sins are like to coſt you;</hi> in which, if we have terrified you to purpoſe, with the juſt apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the manifold Dangers you are in, whilſt you continue in a ſtate of Impenitency, your Humiliation will be <hi>matter of rejoycing</hi> to us; and in the depth of your ſorrow and anguiſh of Spirit, we can ſafely adminiſter this Cordial to revive you:</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="subsection">
                  <p>2. That though <hi>your Danger be great and imminent,</hi> yet there is ſtill, by God's Mercy, a <hi>Poſſibility of your Deliverance</hi> out of it. Were you ſhut up in Everlaſting Miſery, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, we <hi>would not come to torment you before your time:</hi> but, thanks be to God, (whoſe <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is over all his Works</hi>) your caſe is not yet ſo deſperate, but that you may be everlaſtingly ſafe, if you pleaſe. 'Tis too true, that <hi>you are
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:153082:13"/> already in the Fire;</hi> your courſes are as dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and deſtructive as the Fire; you are <hi>in incendio libidinis &amp; obſcaenitatis;</hi> you <hi>burn in your lusts one towards another,</hi> but you may be ſaved for all that: <hi>God wills not the death of a Sinner:</hi> though the Flames of Hell have <hi>ſing'd his Garments that were ſpotted by the Fleſh,</hi> and taken hold of the <hi>Hairs of his Head,</hi> yet God ſincerely deſires that he may be reſcued from Damnation: though he be gone beyond all the Methods and Revelations of his Mercy, and run into the horrible Impieties of <hi>Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, Apoſtacy,</hi> and <hi>Ingratitude;</hi> yet if <hi>he will,</hi> even now at laſt, withdraw his feet from thoſe <hi>Paths that lead to Deſtruction;</hi> or if <hi>we can ſnatch,</hi> or force him from the brink of the Bottomleſs Pit, he is not yet out of the power and poſſibilities of recovering from thoſe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Burnings; <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 15.</note> 
                     <hi>He ſhall ſuffer loſs, but he may be ſaved, yet ſo as by Fire.</hi> If men will leave their Sins whilſt it is called <hi>To Day,</hi> Gods Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments will alſo leave them; for their Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties paſs on to Eternal Flames only by the train of Impenitence; nor can they ever caſt them into Hell, if they repent of them <hi>timely and effectually;</hi> which, that none of us may be tempted to <hi>procraſtinate,</hi> as if there were
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:153082:13"/> no danger of our delay, but haſten to <hi>flee from the wrath to come,</hi> whilſt it is yet to come, let us obſerve in the third place,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="subsection">
                  <p>3. The <hi>difficulty of eſcaping</hi> this their immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and everlaſting deſtruction: Their <hi>Pardon,</hi> as well as themſelves, muſt <hi>be fetched out of the Fire.</hi> They perhaps may ſee no danger in their condition, and as if, like <hi>Salamanders,</hi> they were in their proper Element, may be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed at thoſe who would <hi>pluck them out of the Fire;</hi> but we muſt tell them, that they are loſt and undone for ever, except they be <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed by the Power of God;</hi> nay, 'tis a <hi>miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Grace,</hi> and an <hi>extraordinary change,</hi> which muſt turn the current ſtream of their Iniquity, and their <hi>Salvation muſt be wrought out with</hi> infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite <hi>fear and trembling;</hi> nor is there any en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance for them into Heaven, but by the <hi>ſtrait paſſage</hi> of a <hi>ſecond birth;</hi> the bleſſed opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity whereof if they do <hi>procrastinate,</hi> they may loſe for ever. And therefore,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="subsection">
                  <p>4. By what <hi>Means</hi> we may aſſiſt them in this great Work of their eſcaping, and what is the only poſſible <hi>way to ſave them,</hi> is to be the moſt important inquiry of our whole Lives, it being the greateſt ſervice we can do to God, or them; and if I can either inſtruct or
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:153082:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> quicken you in it, we ſhall both have abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant cauſe to bleſs God for ſo ſeaſonable an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking.</p>
                  <p>Now firſt, we muſt be <hi>earneſt and importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi> with our periſhing Brethren, as the <hi>Angel</hi> was with <hi>Lot, and force them out of Sodom;</hi> Admoniſh them with an holy vehemency to <hi>flee for their lives,</hi> and to eſcape to the Mountain, leſt they be conſum'd; Pull them haſtily, and, with a <hi>charitable violence,</hi> out of their ſins, as a Mother doth her Child out of the fire, when apprehenſive of the danger.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Uſe a <hi>ſharp, quick,</hi> and <hi>cutting reprehenſion;</hi> our words muſt be as <hi>nails driven to the head,</hi> ſo as to be faſtned and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetted in the Soul of a Sinner, and to deſtroy <hi>the Beaſt,</hi> that we may ſave <hi>the Man.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Men muſt firſt be forced and <hi>fired out of themſelves,</hi> or elſe they will never come to <hi>Chriſt:</hi> and, <hi>We</hi> are the <hi>Servants of the moſt high God,</hi> who are <hi>ſent to compel you to come into Heaven,</hi> and to <note place="margin">Acts 16. 17.</note> 
                     <hi>ſhew unto you the way of Salvation.</hi> Our Commiſſion and Inſtructions are to tell you, that if you would be <hi>ſaved from ſuffering,</hi> you muſt alſo be <hi>ſaved from ſinning;</hi> your Lives and your Luſts cannot both be preſerv'd: nor will it be ſufficient that you
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:153082:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> forſake <hi>ſome</hi> of your ſins; but, the <hi>whole body</hi> of them muſt be deſtroyed: You muſt <hi>Crucifie the Old Man,</hi> and <hi>Mortifie every Iniquity which now reigneth in you;</hi> ſo, that unleſs you leave <hi>the Lap of Dalilah,</hi> and be Divorced from your <hi>beloved Herodias,</hi> you cannot be ſaved. You muſt give up <hi>every Traytor</hi> that is Harbour'd in your Boſom, or you cannot be at Peace with the <hi>King of Heaven.</hi> Your <hi>Right Hand muſt be cut off,</hi> and <hi>your Right Eye pulled out,</hi> if they ſtand in oppoſition to the Laws of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> whoſe Dominion you muſt chearfully ſubmit to, <hi>to all intents and purpoſes,</hi> if ever you expect deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance by him.</p>
                  <p>Let not therefore the Voice of your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience be drowned, through the Avocation of <hi>Senſual Pleaſures,</hi> or the hurry of <hi>Worldly Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs,</hi> or the noiſe and clamour of Earthly <hi>Cares, Luſts</hi> or <hi>Affections;</hi> but, give it leave to do its Office, and liſten to what it ſpeaks here, leſt it ſpeak what you would not be willing to hear hereafter. Remember you ſtand now up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your Good-behaviour for Eternity; and, ſuch as your <hi>Preſent Choice</hi> is, will your <hi>Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Condition</hi> be. I wiſh it were in my power to <hi>fright you into your Wits,</hi> and to ſcare you into the way of Salvation. What
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:153082:15"/> will you do <hi>when the Philiſtians are upon you?</hi> When the World ſhall take its <hi>laſt leave</hi> of you? When you muſt bid your Friends, Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and Lands; your Pleaſures, Places and Preferments, Farewel for ever; and, when he who is now <hi>your Tempter,</hi> will prove <hi>your Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentor?</hi> Can you <hi>dwell with Everlaſting Burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings?</hi> Can you <hi>abide the Conſuming Fire?</hi> If not, how can you perſwade your ſelves to live any longer in ſuch a courſe of Life, every Act whereof is a ſtep to Perdition? Unleſs you can perſwade your ſelves, that <hi>God's Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> will <hi>Evacuate his Laws,</hi> and Fruſtrate all the Wiſe Deſigns of his <hi>Juſtice,</hi> you can Dream of no way of Eſcaping. We are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged therefore, for your ſakes, to become <hi>Boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerges, Sons of Thunder;</hi> and, to ſhew you, not only the <hi>Greatneſs,</hi> but the <hi>Preſentneſs of the Danger</hi> you are in; and, to ſet the Terrours of the Almighty continually before your eyes. Thus <hi>Nathan</hi> dealt with <hi>David,</hi> denouncing againſt him God's heavy Judgments; <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>The Sword ſhall never depart from thy Houſe:</hi> and, <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5. 5.</note> St. <hi>Paul delivered up the Inceſtuous Perſon to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, for the deſtruction of the Fleſh, that his Spirit might be ſaved;</hi> and thus did <hi>Jonah</hi> to the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Nineveh,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Jonah 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Yet forty days and the City ſhall</hi>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:153082:15"/> 
                     <hi>be deſtroyed.</hi> Some Spirits will not be <hi>kept out of the Fire,</hi> but by <hi>caſting them into it:</hi> Your terrifying them <hi>with the Flames,</hi> will be a means to keep them <hi>out of them:</hi> A Showre of <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Brimſtone,</hi> ſuch as God rained down upon <hi>Sodom</hi> in the Letter, is beſt for them; if you ſpare them, you deſtroy them. Some Men muſt be <hi>led to Heaven,</hi> by the <hi>way of Hell:</hi> 'tis a very <hi>deſirable fear</hi> which is a means of <hi>pulling Men out of the Fire.</hi> We are <hi>ſaved by Faith,</hi> as that receiveth and taketh hold of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and, we are alſo <hi>ſaved by Fear,</hi> as that taketh hold of us, and drives us to <hi>Chriſt:</hi> By <hi>Faith</hi> we ſee, and apply our help in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and, <hi>by Fear,</hi> we are brought to ſee our need of his help. Thus is a good Heart bettered, by all the Diſpenſations of God, as well by his <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti,</hi> as his <hi>Mercies.</hi> If God <hi>ſpeak Death,</hi> it is an advantage to his Spiritual Life; and, he Mends upon his <hi>Threatnings,</hi> as well as his <hi>Promiſes.</hi> The <hi>Devils</hi> themſelves <hi>believe and tremble;</hi> and, 'tis impoſſible for them to eſcape <hi>Hell,</hi> who come ſhort of the <hi>Religion</hi> of ſuch as are already there. <hi>Quanta damnatio eſt à dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natis damnari?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If therefore we can ſo <hi>humble Men</hi> with Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, that they may <hi>be exalted</hi> in God's good
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:153082:16"/> time, it will be the greateſt kindneſs we can do them: Be the Means never ſo <hi>pungent and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi> the Severities never ſo great; if they be by Experience found <hi>neceſſary,</hi> for the prevention of greater Miſchiefs, they are to be thankfully receiv'd, as Tokens of the ſincereſt Friendſhip: <note place="margin">Prov. 27. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>Faithful are the wounds of a Friend, but the kiſſes of an Enemy are deceitful.</hi> If my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion be falling <hi>into the Fire,</hi> or from a <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipice,</hi> and I, in ſnatching him back, put his Arm out of joynt; Would he call his eſcape, <hi>An unkind Deliverance,</hi> becauſe it coſt him ſome pain? <hi>Phyſitians</hi> muſt not be moved at the Rage or Revilings of their <hi>diſtempered Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients;</hi> but, reſolve to do and ſuffer the utmoſt, before they give them over: and ſo muſt we do, and ſuffer any thing (but Sin) to ſave a Soul from death; we muſt preſcribe Men that, which may be beſt for their Health, how ill ſoever they may take it.</p>
                  <p>But, if we cannot reſcue you out of thoſe <hi>Flames,</hi> nor impoſe the <hi>Kingdom of Heaven</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, by ſuch an <hi>holy violence;</hi> we muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily leave you under greater <hi>Guilt</hi> than we found you; and, your <hi>Pains</hi> will be increaſed even for <hi>the loſs of ours:</hi> It will be a great part of <hi>your Hell,</hi> to think, <hi>what Pains,</hi> and Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:153082:16"/> 
                     <hi>we uſed,</hi> to ſave you from it, and all in vain: How Scornfully you have refuſed our Calls, and Rejected our Importunities? You cannot take a more certain courſe to <hi>deſtroy your ſelves,</hi> and <hi>diſoblige us,</hi> than to turn our <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion</hi> into <hi>Complaints,</hi> and to force us from <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceding for, and with you,</hi> to <hi>accuſe,</hi> and <hi>wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt you;</hi> that, when we had <hi>Invited you to the Marriage-Feaſt,</hi> with all the Earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs imaginable, you would not be <hi>Courted;</hi> no, nor <hi>Compell'd to come in. God,</hi> and your <hi>own Conſciences,</hi> will one day tell you, and all the World, what Overtures of Mercy have been made you, and how plainly and frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you have been <hi>forewarned of the Evil Day;</hi> when, with Fruitleſs Cries and Horrour, you ſhall beſeech, too late, for thoſe Opportunities of <hi>Grace,</hi> which you have ſo long deſpiſed. Now, that it may never be your <hi>Doom,</hi> thus ſturdily <hi>to caſt away your ſelves,</hi> Conſider, <hi>whilſt it is called To Day,</hi> how much it is your <hi>Intereſt,</hi> as well as <hi>your Duty, to hate the very Garment ſpotted by the Fleſh:</hi> The Explication of which <hi>Phraſe,</hi> is the laſt thing premiſed, and that which may ſerve for the <hi>Application</hi> of the <hi>Text.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:153082:17"/>
               <p>4. <hi>Hating the</hi> very <hi>Garment ſpotted by the Fleſh.</hi> 'Tis a <hi>Proverbial Speech;</hi> whereby is ſignified, the abhorrency which we ought to have, of any the leaſt degree of Uncleanneſs, in alluſion to the prohibited, and unclean Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the <hi>Leprous</hi> perſon; <note place="margin">Lev. 13. 47. Heb. 12. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>looking diligently, leſt any root of bitterneſs ſpringing up trouble you, and thereby many be defiled: Putting off the old man with his deeds;</hi> that is, all evil Affections, and ſeparating our ſelves <note place="margin">Verſ. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>from thoſe filthy dreams that defile the Fleſh.</hi> Deal not with them as <hi>Companions,</hi> but <hi>Phyſitians;</hi> beware of <hi>catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> that Infection which you come to <hi>cure:</hi> Draw them out of the <hi>Fire,</hi> if you can; but, let them not pull you in too.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aeth.</note> 
                  <hi>Et intuentes in tegumento ſuo maculam ſcorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis ſuae.</hi> The <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> defil'd, not only their <hi>Manners and Actions,</hi> but alſo <hi>their very Garments;</hi> and, I wiſh I could ſay, that, <hi>This Age</hi> were not ſtain'd with <hi>that,</hi> or a <hi>greater <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs.</hi> When <hi>Chriſt</hi> aroſe from the Dead, <hi>he left his Winding-ſheet behind him;</hi> and ſo, in the Spiritual Reſurrection, muſt we leave <hi>the Garments of the Old Man</hi> behind us. <hi>Odio haben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, non ſolum turpia facta carnis, ſed etiam quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid ullo modo ad turpitudinem pertinet. Abſtain from all appearnace of evil;</hi> from whatſoever
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:153082:17"/> hath a ſhew of it, <note place="margin">1 Theſſ, 5. 22.</note> and is liable to miſconſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; not only from the <hi>Crime it ſelf,</hi> but from <hi>every Inſtrument of it,</hi> from every path which leads to it; from all Incentives, Occaſions, and Inducements, from whatſoever may begin, or promote, becauſe all theſe things are of the ſame <hi>Nature</hi> with it. Some few there were, even in <hi>Sardis,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 3. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>who had not defiled their Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:</hi> and, I hope, there are ſome <hi>few</hi> among us, who have <hi>eſcap'd the Pollutions of this World, through the knowledge of our Saviour;</hi> and, who <hi>live</hi> like Men who are ſatisfied, that they <hi>muſt live</hi> to all Eternity: And, the leſs appearance there is of a <hi>General Innocence,</hi> or a <hi>Publick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> among us, the more doth it concern every private Man, to <hi>waſh his Hands in inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency,</hi> or his <hi>Heart</hi> in <hi>Penitential Tears,</hi> becauſe, it may be, God will <hi>Save the whole Nation</hi> for the <hi>Repentance of a few;</hi> He may hear the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of <hi>Ten</hi> for a <hi>City,</hi> though the Generality of them ſhould remain Unreformed: All <hi>his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-paſſengers lives were bestowed upon St.</hi> Paul; <hi>Sodom</hi> had been ſaved if <hi>Ten Penitents</hi> had been in it; and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> if but <hi>One:</hi> Or, if the Lord be ſo peremptorily bent to bring in ſuch a <hi>General Judgment,</hi> that though <hi>Moſes,</hi> or <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel;</hi> though <hi>Noah, Daniel</hi> or <hi>Job</hi> were among
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:153082:18"/> them, <hi>they</hi> ſhould not prevail for the ſaving of others, yet at leaſt we ſhould <hi>ſave our own Souls</hi> alive; eſpecially if we left our Sins out of <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect hatred,</hi> before they left us. The <hi>Old Man</hi> may be ſorry, that he cannot be Young; and, the <hi>Sick Man,</hi> that he cannot Revel as his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions; but, it is not a <hi>Principle of Conſcience</hi> which makes either of them forſake their <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitual Sins;</hi> nor do they <hi>hate</hi> them, as Men Thoroughly Convinced of the manifold Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of every Particular Iniquity muſt needs do.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Let us not <hi>put it off till to Morrow;</hi> for, we know not where the next Night may lodge us: but conſider, The <hi>Hourly Poſsibilities of Death;</hi> and, The <hi>Succeeding State of Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which will Revenge, with moſt Severe Inflictions, the few <hi>Minutes</hi> of our Reprieve: Then ſhall we endeavour our <hi>Own,</hi> and <hi>Other Mens</hi> Salvation with <hi>fear and compaſsion,</hi> and be ſollicitous to <hi>pull</hi> them and our ſelves <hi>out of the Fire;</hi> and let all who ſhall make an Inſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction into our Lives, ſee, That <hi>we hate even the Garment ſpotted by the Fleſh;</hi> and, That we are <hi>led by the holy Spirit of God,</hi> in that <hi>Good Old Way,</hi> which leads to Life, and that Eternal.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:153082:18"/>
               <p>I ſhall cloſe this Diſcourſe, as our Apoſtle does this Epiſtle: <note place="margin">Verſ. 24, 25.</note> 
                  <hi>Now unto him, who is able to keep us from falling, and to preſent us faultleſs before the Preſence of his Glory with exceeding Joy,; To the only wiſe God our Saviour, be Glory and Majeſty, Dominion and Power, now and ever,</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:153082:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
